<data>

	<event
		start="1796"
 		end="1799"
		title = "Panic of 1797"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Just as a land speculation bubble was bursting, deflation from the Bank of England (which was facing insolvency because of the cost of Great Britain's involvement in the French Revolutionary Wars) crossed to North America and disrupted market|commercial and real estate markets in the United States and the Caribbean, and caused a Panic of 1797|major financial panic.  Prosperity continued in the south, but economic activity was stagnant in the north for three years.  The young United States engaged in the Quasi-War with France
	</event>
	<event
		start="1802"
 		end="1804"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		A boom of war-time activity led to a decline after the Peace of Amiens ended the French Revolutionary Wars|war between the United Kingdom and France.  Commodity prices fell dramatically.  Trade was disrupted by pirates, leading to the First Barbary War.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1807"
 		end="1810"
		title = "Depression of 1807"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		The Embargo Act of 1807 was passed by the United States Congress under President Thomas Jefferson as tensions increased with the United Kingdom.  Along with trade restrictions imposed by the British, shipping-related industries were hard hit. The Federalist Party (United States)|Federalists fought the embargo and allowed smuggling to take place in New England.  Trade volumes, commodity prices and securities prices all began to fall.  Macon's Bill Number 2 ended the embargoes in May 1810, and a recovery started.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1815"
 		end="1821"
		title = "1815-21 depression"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Shortly after the war ended on March 23, 1815, the United States entered a period of financial panic as bank notes rapidly depreciated because of inflation following the war.  The 1815 panic was followed by several years of mild depression, and then a major financial crisis&nbsp;- the Panic of 1819, which featured widespread foreclosures, bank failures, unemployment, a collapse in real estate prices, and a slump in agriculture and manufacturing.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1822"
 		end="1823"
		title = "1822-1823 recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		After only a mild recovery following the lengthy 1815-21 depression, commodity prices hit a peak in March 1822 and began to fall.  Many businesses failed, unemployment rose and an increase in imports worsened the trade balance.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1825"
 		end="1826"
		title = "1825-1826 recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		The Panic of 1825, a stock crash following a bubble of speculative investments in Latin America led to a decline in business activity in the United States and England.  The recession coincided with a major panic, the date of which may be more easily determined than general cycle changes associated with other recessions.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1828"
 		end="1829"
		title = "1828-1829 recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		In 1826 England forbid the United States to trade with English colonies and in 1827 the United States adopted a counter-prohibition.  Trade declined, just as credit became tight for manufacturers in New England.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1833"
 		end="1834"
		title = "1833-34 recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		The United States' economy declined moderately in 1833-34.  News accounts of the time confirm the slowdown.  The subsequent expansion was driven by land speculation.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1836"
 		end="1838"
		title = "A sharp downturn in the Economy of the United States"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		American economy was caused by bank failures and lack of confidence in the Banknote|paper currency. Speculation markets were greatly affected when Specie Circular|American banks stopped payment in Currency|specie (gold and silver coinage). Over 600 banks failed in this period.  In the south the cotton market completely collapsed.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1839"
 		end="1843"
		title = "Depression"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		This was one of the longest and deepest depressions. It was a period of pronounced deflation and massive default on debt.  The Cleveland Trust Company Index showed the economy spent 68 months below its trend and only 9 months above it. The Index declined 34.3% during this depression.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1845"
 		end="1846"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		This recession was mild enough that it may have only been a slowdown in the growth cycle.  One theory holds that this would have been a recession, except the United States began to gear up for the Mexican-American War which began April 25, 1846.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1847"
 		end="1848"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		The Cleveland Trust Company Index declined 19.7% during 1847 and 1848.  It is associated with a Panic of 1847|financial crisis in Great Britain. in
	</event>
	<event
		start="1853"
 		end="1854"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Interest rates rose in this period, contributing to a decrease in railroad investment.  Security prices fell during this period.  With the exception of falling business investment there is little evidence of contraction in this period.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1857"
 		end="1858"
		title = "Panic of 1857"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Failure of the Ohio Life Insurance and Trust Company burst a European speculative bubble in Rail transport in the United States|United States' railroads and caused a loss of confidence in Banking in the United States|American banks. Over 5,000 businesses failed within the first year of the Panic, and unemployment was accompanied by protest meetings in urban areas.  This is the earliest recession to which the NBER assigns specific months (rather than years) for the peak and trough.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1860"
 		end="1861"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		There was a recession before the American Civil War, which began April 12, 1861.  Zarnowitz says the data generally show a contraction occurred in this period, but it was quite mild.  A financial panic was narrowly averted in 1860 by the first use of clearing house (finance)|clearing house certificates between banks.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1865"
 		end="1867"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		The American Civil War ended in April 1865 and the country entered a lengthy period of general deflation that lasted until 1896.  The United States occasionally experienced periods of recession during the Reconstruction era of the United States|Reconstruction era.  Production increased in the years following the Civil War, but the country still had financial difficulties.  The post-war period coincided with a period of some Panic of 1866|international financial instability.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1869"
 		end="1870"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		A few years after the Civil War, a short recession occurred.  It was unusual since it came amid a period when railroad investment was greatly accelerating, even producing the First Transcontinental Railroad.  The railroads built in this period opened up the interior of the country, giving birth to the Farmers' movement.  The recession may be explained partly by ongoing financial difficulties following the war, which discouraged businesses from building up inventories.  Several months into the recession there was a Black Friday (1869)|major financial panic.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1873"
 		end="1879"
		title = "Long Depression"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Economic problems in Europe prompted the failure of Jay Cooke|Jay Cooke &amp; Company, the largest bank in the United States, which burst the post-American Civil War|Civil War Speculation|speculative bubble. The Coinage Act of 1873 also contributed by immediately depressing the price of silver, which hurt North American mining interests.  The deflation and wage cuts of the era led to labor turmoil, such as the Great Railroad Strike of 1877.  In 1879, the United States returned to the gold standard with the Specie Payment Resumption Act.  This is the longest period of economic contraction recognized by the NBER.  The Long Depression is sometimes held to be the entire period from 1873-96.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1882"
 		end="1885"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Like the Long Depression that preceded it, the recession of 1882-85 was more of a deflation|price depression than a production depression.  From 1879 to 1882 there had been a boom in railroad construction which came to an end, resulting in a decline in both railroad construction and in related industries, particularly iron and steel.  A major economic event during the recession was the Panic of 1884.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1887"
 		end="1888"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Investments in railroads and buildings weakened during this period.  This slowdown was so mild that it is not always considered a recession.  Contemporary accounts apparently indicate it was considered a slight recession.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1890"
 		end="1891"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Although shorter than the recession in 1887-88 and still modest, a slowdown in 1890-91 was somewhat more pronounced than the preceding recession.  International monetary disturbances are blamed for this recession, such as the Panic of 1890 in the United Kingdom.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1893"
 		end="1894"
		title = "Panic of 1893"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Failure of the United States Reading Railroad and withdrawal of European investment led to a Panic of 1893|stock market and banking collapse. This Panic was also precipitated in part by a Bank run|run on the gold supply.  The Treasury had to issue bonds to purchase enough gold.  Profits, investment and income all fell, leading to political instability, the height of Populist Party (United States)|the U.S. populist movement and the Free Silver movement.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1893"
 		end="1897"
		title = "Panic of 1896"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		The period of 1893-97 is seen as a generally depressed cycle that had a short spurt of growth in the middle, following the Panic of 1893. Production shrank and deflation reigned.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1899"
 		end="1900"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		This was a mild recession in the period of general growth beginning after 1897.  Evidence for a recession in this period does not show up in some annual data series.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1902"
 		end="1904"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Though not severe, this downturn lasted for nearly two years and saw a distinct decline in the national product.  Industrial and commercial production both declined, albeit fairly modestly.  The recession came about a year after a Panic of 1901|1901 stock crash.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1907"
 		end="1908"
		title = "Panic of 1907"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		A run on Knickerbocker Trust Company deposits on October 22, 1907, set events in motion that would lead to a severe monetary contraction.  The fallout from the panic led to Congress History of the Federal Reserve System|creating the Federal Reserve System.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1910"
 		end="1911"
		title = "Panic of 1910-1911"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		This was a mild but lengthy recession.  The national product grew by less than 1%, and commercial activity and industrial activity declined.  The period was also marked by deflation.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1913"
 		end="1914"
		title = "Recession of 1913-1914"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Productions and real income declined during this period and were not offset until the start of World War I increased demand. Incidentally, the Federal Reserve Act was signed during this recession, creating the Federal Reserve System, the culmination of a sequence of events following the Panic of 1907.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1918"
 		end="1919"
		title = "Post-World War I recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Severe hyperinflation in Europe took place over production in North America. This was a brief but very sharp recession and was caused by the end of wartime production, along with an influx of labor from returning troops. This in turn caused high unemployment.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1920"
 		end="1921"
		title = "Depression of 1920-21"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		The 1921 recession began a mere 10 months after the post-World War I recession, as the economy continued working through the shift to a peacetime economy.  The recession was short but extremely painful.  The year 1920 was the single most deflationary year in American History; production, however, did not fall as much as might be expected from the deflation.  GNP may have declined between 2.5 and 7 percent, even as wholesale prices declined by 36.8%.  The economy had a strong recovery following the recession. in
	</event>
	<event
		start="1923"
 		end="1924"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		From the depression of 1920-21 until the Great Depression, an era dubbed the Roaring Twenties, the economy was generally expanding.  Industrial production declined in 1923-24, but on the whole this was a mild recession.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1926"
 		end="1927"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		This was an unusual and mild recession, thought to be caused largely because Henry Ford closed production in his factories for six months to switch from production of the Model T to the Ford Model A (1927-1931)|Model A.  Charles P. Kindleberger says the period from 1925 to the start of the Great Depression is best thought of as a boom, and this minor recession just proof that the boom "was not general, uninterrupted or extensive".
	</event>
	<event
		start="1929"
 		end="1933"
		title = "Wall Street Crash of 1929 and Great Depression"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Stock markets crashed worldwide. A banking collapse took place in the United States. Smoot-Hawley Tariff Act|Extensive new tariffs and Causes of the Great Depression|other factors contributed to an extremely deep depression.  The United States did remain in a depression until World War II. In 1936, unemployment fell to 16.9% but later returned to 19% in 1938 (near 1933 levels.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1937"
 		end="1938"
		title = "Recession of 1937"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		US: The Recession of 1937 is only considered minor when compared to the Great Depression, but is otherwise among the worst recessions of the 20th century.  Three explanations are offered for the recession: that tight fiscal policy from an attempt to balance the budget after the expansion of the New Deal caused recession, that tight monetary policy from the Federal Reserve caused the recession, or that declining profits for businesses led to a reduction in investment.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1945"
 		end="1945"
		title = "Recession of 1945"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		The decline in government spending at the end of World War II led to an enormous drop in gross domestic product making this technically a recession.  This was the result of demobilization and the shift from a wartime to peacetime economy.  The post-war years were unusual in a number of ways (unemployment was never high) and this era may be considered a "''sui generis'' end-of-the-war recession".
	</event>
	<event
		start="1948"
 		end="1949"
		title = "Recession of 1949"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		The 1948 recession was a brief economic downturn; forecasters of the time expected much worse, perhaps influenced by the poor economy in their recent lifetime. The recession began shortly after Harry Truman|President Truman's "Fair Deal" economic reforms.  The recession also followed a period of monetary tightening.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1957"
 		end="1958"
		title = "Recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Monetary policy was tightened during the two years preceding 1957, followed by an easing of policy at the end of 1957. The budget balance resulted in a change in budget surplus of 0.8% of GDP in 1957 to a budget deficit of 0.6% of GDP in 1958, and then to 2.6% of GDP in 1959.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1960"
 		end="1961"
		title = "Recession of 1960-61"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		Another primarily monetary recession occurred after the Federal Reserve began raising interest rates in 1959.  The government switched from deficit (or 2.6% in 1959) to surplus (of 0.1% in 1960).  When the economy emerged from this short recession it began the second longest period of growth in NBER history.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1969"
 		end="1970"
		title = "Recession of 1969-70"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		The relatively mild 1969 recession followed a lengthy expansion.  At the end of the expansion inflation was rising, possibly a result of increased deficits.  This relatively mild recession coincided with an attempt to start closing the budget deficits of the Vietnam War (fiscal tightening) and the Federal Reserve raising interest rates (monetary tightening).
	</event>
	<event
		start="1973"
 		end="1975"
		title = "1973-75 recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		A quadrupling of oil prices by OPEC coupled with high government spending because of the Vietnam War led to stagflation in the United States. The period was also marked by the 1973 oil crisis and the 1973-1974 stock market crash.  The period is remarkable for rising unemployment coinciding with rising inflation.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1981"
 		end="1982"
		title = "1980s recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		The Iranian Revolution sharply increased the price of oil around the world in 1979, causing the 1979 energy crisis. This was caused by the new regime in power in Iran, which exported oil at inconsistent intervals and at a lower volume, forcing prices up. Tight monetary policy in the United States to control inflation led to another recession. The changes were made largely because of inflation carried over from the previous decade because of the 1973 oil crisis and the 1979 energy crisis.
	</event>
	<event
		start="1990"
 		end="1991"
		title = "Early 1990s recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		After the lengthy peacetime expansion of the 1980s, inflation began to increase and the Federal Reserve responded by raising interest rates from 1986 to 1989.  This weakened but did not stop growth, but some combination of the subsequent 1990 oil price shock, the debt accumulation of the 1980s, new banking regulations following the Savings and loan crisis|S&L Crisis and growing consumer pessimism combined with the weakened economy to produce a brief recession.
	</event>
	<event
		start="2001"
 		end="2001"
		title = "Early 2000s recession"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		The 1990s were the longest period of growth in American history.  The collapse of the speculative dot-com bubble, a fall in business outlays and investments, and the economic effects arising from the September 11 attacks|September 11th attacks, brought the decade of growth to an end.  Despite these major shocks, the recession was brief and shallow.
	</event>
	<event
		start="2007"
 		end="2009"
		title = "Subprime crisis"
		link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_recessions_in_the_United_States"
		>
		The subprime mortgage crisis led to the collapse of the United States housing bubble.  Falling housing-related assets contributed to a Financial crisis of 2007-2010|global financial crisis, even as oil and food prices soared.  The crisis led to the failure or collapse of many of the United States' largest financial institutions: Bear Stearns, Fannie Mae, Freddie Mac, Lehman Brothers and American International Group|AIG, as well as a crisis in the Automotive industry crisis of 2008-2009|automobile industry.  The government responded with an unprecedented Troubled Asset Relief Program|$700 billion bank bailout and American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009|$787 billion fiscal stimulus package. The National Bureau of Economic Research declared the end of this recession over a year after the end date.
	</event>
</data>